So I just wanted to show you.
So this is the new GUI that
Lily was talking about.
This is not the one on JuliaHub,
because there's a few things
that are not yet working.
But you can see
that we essentially
have a flat map, a flat brain.
And if you hover over
any brain region,
you can see essentially
the description.
And then if you
let's say you want
to place a block on
the GUI, then you
can place the icon there and
then you can make connections,
something like this.
And the connections
are typically
done with Alt or Option.
It depends on-- I think,
in Windows it's Alt right.
And then on the Mac it's
Option, something like this.
And I just wanted to show you--
let me actually get my mouse.
Here it is.
OK, so everybody got
this thing running?
No, this is the wrong one.
Apps, JuliaHub.
So this is the JuliaHub app.
And once you're here, you can--
as soon as you take
the coupon, you
have access to the
Neuroblox application
and you can launch it.
And when you connect,
then it will say
connect into your application.
And it will take a while,
because what happens in the AWS,
it has to reserve a computer
and get all the resources.
But while we do this,
what I'm going to do
is I have a little
presentation to give you
the GUI introduction.
Here we go.
OK, so this is
the Neuroblox GUI.
I'm really thankful to
JuliaHub because they
were very generous of giving
all these computational coupons.
And the plan is to actually
have it permanently
hosted in JuliaHub.
So the user
interface in general,
if you have icons on the
screen, the way to get edges
is by Alt or Option.
If you click on
an icon with Alt,
then you get a self-interaction.
So you get essentially an arrow
that points to the same icon.
And if you do Alt drag,
you create an edge
from one icon to the other.
Left click on icon is select.
Left click on edge is select.
And left click
drag on edge anchor
changes the shape so you
can move around the edges.
And I will show this.
Then the sidebar, we
have-- on the sidebar,
we have several tabs.
One is node and edges, which
when you click on a node, then
it shows you the
properties of the node.
It shows you the parameters.
You can change the parameters.
The same is true for the edges.
If you have edges, you can give
the properties of the edges.
Then we have a section
on parameters, where you
can create custom parameters.
So you can essentially say--
let's say I create
a parameter that
controls all the connections.
So all the connections
are changed the same way.
There's simulation
settings, parameter fitting.
I don't think that parameter
fitting is functional right now.
So I don't think you should do
any parameter fitting right now.
Also, reinforcement
learning I don't
think we have much experience
with this particular GUI.
It was working at one point.
But Neuroblox is
constantly evolving.
And so what I wanted to
do with you actually,
is a very simple example.
And that is called the harmonic
oscillator neural mass model.
This is sort of a toy
neural math model.
There are some works that
use the harmonic oscillator.
But I think actually it's a very
good example for just testing
out your intuition,
because it's almost
like a harmonic oscillator.
But it's kind of a nonlinear
harmonic oscillator.
And you have to--
the challenge is to
get this to oscillate.
If you know
differential equations,
you can actually see that
there's a dxdt is equal to y,
and then dydt is minus omega
squared times x, omega squared
times x, which means that
if you take the derivative
and plug it in, then you
get essentially a harmonic
oscillator, like
differential equation, where
the solution of that would be a
sine or cosine with a frequency
omega.
But then you have other terms.
You have essentially
a damping term.
So this thing alone would be a
damped oscillator would never
actually oscillate properly.
But then you have a connection
which is A10 of the junction.
And the junction could be then
the input of something else.
So in order to get
this oscillate,
you have to actually have two
of the harmonic oscillators
interacting with each other.
So there could be a self
interaction and a interaction
between the oscillators.
And I will show you how
to construct this system
and how to get them to behave.
And so the challenge
for you maybe
as an intellectual
challenge, how do we
change the frequency of
these harmonic oscillators?
That would be a little test.
And then the next step
that we want to do
is we want to build
a cortical region.
And we are not going to
do this hierarchically,
not like in the tutorial.
But what I wanted to do--
what I want you to do
is to essentially build
a cortical region where
you specify essentially
how many winner takes
all circuits you use
and then build it
and simulate it.
And this is what the
ultimate goal will be.
You will have two
cortical regions
that are combined to each other
or connected to each other.
And you will be able to
see the adjacency matrix
of that coupling.
So this over here
essentially means
the lower half is
C1, where you see
all the connections
between neurons
within a cortical region.
Then you will see
on the top right you
see all the connections of C2.
And then in yellow are
all the connections
between the cortical regions.
And this is the flat brain GUI.
Let's see whether the
thing has started up.
Here, this is now JuliaHub.
And so what we're going to do
is we're creating a new project.
And the first one is we wanted
to do harmonic oscillators.
Click OK.
And then after some
time, you see the canvas.
So on the left side,
we have a canvas.
By the way, this is
just the background.
The flat brain is actually
a real representation
of the brain.
This is just nice looking.
And then I just
wanted to make you
aware of all the
parts of the GUI.
So you have over
here the sidebar
with all the different tabs,
nodes and edges, parameters,
simulation.
In simulation you
can, for example,
say the duration, the
relative tolerance,
the absolute tolerance.
You can specify the
solver, whether it's
a stiff solver or
a non-stiff solver,
and also the time interval.
By the way, in Neuroblox the
time unit is milliseconds.
So one is one millisecond.
We have to make this decision.
And so in order to place
something on the canvas,
you just pick something
from here, from the bottom.
And where is the
harmonic oscillator?
So here you click on
the harmonic oscillator.
And then you see an icon.
And then you can move the
icon around, like this.
I also would recommend
that you rename this thing.
So why don't we call this
harmonic oscillator one,
like this.
And then let's say we are
going to take another harmonic
oscillator and place it on the
canvas two and then call it HO2.
So now you have two
harmonic oscillators.
Now, I told you how
to create edges.
Edges you click Alt or Option.
You click on the node and then
you see a self-interaction,
like this.
You can actually click on
this little handle here.
And then you can drag
it around, like this.
I like to have them on the side.
Then you create another
self-interaction
on the other side.
And then you can drag from
one icon to the other,
dragging essentially
connections.
And then you can move them out.
Was everybody able to do this?
Are you trying to?
Anyway, if you don't try it
now, you can try it later.
You have access to JuliaHub
for the whole week,
actually, until your
coupon runs out,
until you spend $50 on
computational resources.
Now what we want to do is
we want to set the strength.
So you click on the edge.
You go to nodes and edges
and you pick a weight.
And I would recommend
starting maybe
with something like minus 1.
Self-interaction is inhibitory.
And then what you can do is you
can put a weight of, I think,
5 and 6.
And this is just my
personal choice here.
And then what you can do is
once you set the whole system up
with all the connections,
you can run a simulation.
You click on Run
Simulation over here.
And then the simulation
result will be over here.
Now, just one of the
details about Julia.
Julia is just-in-time
compiled language,
which means that whenever you
execute something in Julia,
it compiles at that time, which
means that because this is also
running in the cloud, it will
take a little while until all
the differential equation
or JL packages are compiled.
So next time you do
this, it's much faster.
So it will take a while.
So by the way, one of
the interesting details
about this GUI is that, and
this is why we didn't even
know that we can host it,
is because there's actually
three web servers that are
interacting with each other.
This is a very, very
complicated GUI.
It has a server for
the graphics and it
has a server for the front
end, which is a view framework.
And then it also has a
Julia back end server.
And they are all
talking to each other.
And so for example,
here what happened
is that the simulation
was finished.
And now the data is being
sent to the server that
does the graphics.
And now the graphics server
has returned the graphics.
So this is the output.
So you essentially see the
two states that are almost
on top of each other.
And you can then take this graph
and move it to the other side.
You can enlarge it.
You can click it from
one side to the other.
And then you can essentially,
select one of the nodes
and change parameters
within the nodes.
So if you want to test
whether one of the parameters,
if you change the
parameter a little bit,
run the simulation again,
and then see what happens.
And now you have actually
a much better oscillation
or a much more
stable oscillation.
And your challenge
will be for maybe later
to see if you build a model like
this, how can you, let's say,
double the frequency
of the system?
So let me-- what's the time?
When are we ending?
In 10 minutes?
So now what I want
to do is to actually,
let's just create
another project.
I wanted to show you,
give you a little demo
of the cortical regions.
So we'll create a new
project, cortical demo.
And the demo is
actually super simple,
because what we
can do is we can--
we have a whole section
of composite blocks.
Composite blocks are blocks
that are made from other blocks.
And there's actually
a cortical block here.
And we can just put that here.
Maybe we can call it C1 And here
on the parameters of the node,
you can see there's a
number of winner takes all.
So you have 10 winner
take all circuits.
I would recommend to reduce that
to five because 10 winner takes
all takes longer to simulate.
And I wouldn't actually
change anything else,
just run the simulation.
And this is one of the
glitches, by the way,
of the GUI, because it
thinks that it has already
there's some data in the
pipeline that it thought.
So sometimes you have to just
click on Run simulation one more
time to get the new parameters.
I thought we had taken care
of this, but we didn't.
So this is now the simulation
of a cortical region.
So you can see the initial
conditions were not quite right.
But then essentially
after like 50 milliseconds
it established a nice--
this is, by the way, the average
voltage of the cortical region.
And then what you can do is you
can go to here to special plots.
And there's a raster
plot that we can do.
A raster plot is essentially,
it picks a certain number
of neurons within the--
no.
It looks at the
spiking of the neurons.
And the stack plot gives you
spiking of individual neurons.
And you can actually
specify how many
neurons you want to look at.
And then the adjacency matrix
gives you the connectivity
within the region.
So this is random.
I mean, [INAUDIBLE] essentially
created an algorithm to say,
if I want a certain
density of connections,
then it takes random
connections within the--
and these are only the
excitatory neurons.
And let's hide this plot and
let's create another region.
So if we wanted to do another
cortical region over here,
let's call this C2.
Oh, yeah, actually,
you're right.
So if you're here
right, let's say here,
we can also look at
the power spectrum.
And again, it has to communicate
with the graph server
and come back.
We'll try to get better at this.
So this is now the
power spectrum.
And you can see the alpha band,
beta band, and gamma band.
Oh, yeah.
And the other thing is
I don't think it works--
if you do the harmonic
oscillator again,
click on the show latex,
latex so you can actually look
at the equations of the system.
You can also export
data to your desktop.
So let's get back
to the other region.
So let's say this
is the C2 region.
We may also make it small so
that it's easily simulatable.
And then what we're
doing is we are clicking.
Essentially, we're going from
one region to another region.
Click on it and
create a weight, let's
say, 1.5 so that we
see a difference.
And by the way,
again, the density
is a measure of how many
connections will be made.
And then we Run
Simulation again.
And you can play
around with this.
The only thing I'm
warning you, if you
make these regions
too big, then it
will take a long
time to simulate.
By the way, Harris,
the compilation
is already using graph
dynamics for cortical regions
internally, if you
say system from graph?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, you have to flag it.
So just for your
information, I'm
not using the optimized
optimize compilation.
So the GUI is actually
slower than it should be.
So this is, again, so
these are the two regions.
And if we click on any
of the cortical regions,
you can actually see the
adjacency matrix of all three,
of all two regions and
the cross correlations.
Show plot.
Here we go.
So again, this is the
one region and then
the connections between the
regions and the other regions
And that's pretty much
what I wanted to show you.
You can also hide plot.
If you want it to be really
adventurous, what you could do
is, even though I think
I have to give you
a file for the images, but you
remember that Lily showed you
about [INAUDIBLE]?
So what we can
essentially do is we
can take an image stimulus
block and place it here and then
connect it to the visual
cortex, and then essentially,
show the visual cortex images.
And then that image gets then
sent to the prefrontal cortex.
But if you actually if
you wanted to try this,
then I can give you our
images and you can try this.
Anyway, so that was all
I wanted to show you.
And again, feel free to
play around with the GUI.
Once we get into
tutorials, you may just
want to try some of the winner
takes all circuit, for example,
in the GUI.
So are there maybe
questions that you have?